Guide to the Louis Agassiz Fuertes papers, 1892-1954
Fuertes, Louis Agassiz papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Louis Agassiz Fuertes papers, 1892-1954, 1892-1927 (bulk)
2662
Louis Agassiz Fuertes, 1874-1927
c. 35 cubic ft.; 25 Map case folders
Notes, notebooks, journals, sketchbooks, diaries, articles, photographs, negatives, letters, artwork.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The papers of Louis Agassiz Fuertes (1874-1927), an ornithologist and a painter of birds. Includes student notes, notebooks, journals and sketchbooks; diaries; journals from expedition, many including sketches; notes; articles by and about Fuertes. The collection also contains artwork.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
FUERTES, LOUIS AGASSIZ (February 7, 1874-August 22, 1927), artist-naturalist, was born at Ithaca, N.Y. His father, Estevan Antonio Fuertes, was a descendant of a prominent Spanish family. His mother, Mary Stone Perry Fuertes, of Dutch and English ancestry, was born in Troy, N.Y. His talent in drawing and his love of birds began to show at an early age and developed without particular encouragement from parents or friends. By the time he was eight or nine years old he had definitely focused his attention upon painting birds, and when he was fourteen, according to an autobiographical sketch, his career was definitely settled. He received his education in the public schools of Ithaca, N.Y., then in 1892 accompanied his parents to Europe and spent the year in a preparatory school in Zurich, Switzerland. On his return he entered Cornell University and was graduated with the class of 1897. In 1894, while on a glee club trip to Washington, D.C., he met Elliott Coues and showed him some of his paintings. The encouragement which he received from the ornithologist was apparently a deciding factor in his career. Following his graduation from Cornell he spent a year studying with Abbott H. Thayer, which improved his technique very materially, and with him and his son, Gerald Thayer, he went to Florida in the spring of 1898. This was the first of a series of expeditions which widened his knowledge of the birds of North America. In 1899 he went to Alaska with the famed Harriman expedition, and two years later be visited western Texas and New Mexico with a party from the United States Biological Survey. With Dr. F.M. Chapman, curator of birds at the American Museum in New York City, between 1902 and 1913 he visited the Bahamas, the Pacific Coast, the prairies of Saskatchewan and the Canadian Rockies, the Cuthbert Rookery in Florida, Yucatan and eastern Mexico, and Colombia, South America. In addition to these expeditions Fuertes visited Jamaica on his wedding journey in 1904; the Magdalen Islands and Bird Rock in 1909 with Leonard Cutler Sanford; and after a dozen years spent mostly in his studio at Ithaca, in 1926-27 he made an expedition to little-known parts of Abyssinia with Dr. Wilfred H. Osgood for the Field Museum of Natural History in Chicago. From 1923 to 1927 he was lecturer in ornithology at Cornell University.
Fuertes was a tireless worker in the field and never lost an opportunity to add to his collection of birds or sketches. At the time of his death he left a collection of some 3,500 beautifully prepared bird skins and over a thousand field and studio sketches of more than 400 different kinds of birds. His greatest collection, however, was the series of mental images of each bird which seemed to be indelibly impressed upon his mind with all the accuracy of a photographic plate. When examining a bird, his concentration was supreme; he was oblivious to everything about him; and during these moments, apparently, details of pose and expression were so fixed in his mind that years afterwards he could reproduce them with his pencil and brush without the slightest hesitation. His paintings, which illustrate most of the leading bird books published between 1896 and 1927, are characterized by a beauty of draftsmanship and a devotion to truth which are manifested not only in the accuracy of every detail of plumage and form, but in the perfection attained in reproducing the characteristic attitudes and expressions of each species. On June 2, 1904, Fuertes was married to Margaret F. Sumner of Ithaca, by whom he had two children. He was killed in a grade-crossing accident in 1927.
[Biographical Note written by Arthur A. Allen and taken from The Dictionary of American Biography, vol. VII (Charles Scribner's Sons: New York, 1931), p.53.]
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, often illustrated and including anecdotes and descriptions of expeditions, with ornithologists, fellow artists, and naturalists, especially on the subject of bird coloration and "concealing coloration"; personal correspondence on the Savage Club of Ithaca; and letters to his daughter, Mary Fuertes Boynton, from Fuertes' friends and colleagues about Fuertes and his work. Student notes, notebooks, journals and sketchbooks; diaries; journals from expeditions, many including sketches; notes; articles by and about Fuertes; photographs of Fuertes; photographs taken by him on expeditions to South America, Mexico and the Caribbean; photographic negatives of Fuertes' sketches; color proofs of reproductions of Fuertes' paintings; and several sketchbooks. Artwork includes over 1,000 pieces, most of which are pencil, ink, or preliminary watercolor sketches of birds, groups of birds, and anatomical details; over 100 are finished watercolors and chalk drawings. Includes Fuertes' pocket knife. Major correspondents include Richard E. Bishop, Mary Fuertes Boynton, Courtenay Brandreth, Frank M. Chapman, Elliot Coues, E.H. Forbush, Witmer Stone, George Miksch Sutton, Abbott Thayer and Hendrik Willem van Loon. Also one copper printing plate of L.A.F. holding a bird. Also a Great Horned Owl print by Beck Engraving Philadelphia numbered 38 of 1500.
Two volume souvenir album entitled "A Souvenir of the Harriman Alaska Expedition, May - August 1899," "Volume 1, New York to Cook Inlet" and "Volume II, Cook Inlet to Bering Strait and the Return Voyage," includes ca. 254 photographs taken primarily by Edward S. Curtis and C. Hart Merriam and compiled by Edward H. Harriman for expedition participants of Arctic landscapes, people, plants, and animals as well as a map of the expedition route. Also shows expedition members including Harriman and family, John Burroughs, John Muir, Benjamin K. Emerson, and Louis Agassiz Fuertes. Photographs are identified.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Fuertes, Louis Agassiz, 1874-1927; Boynton, Mary Fuertes; Bishop, Richard E; Brandreth, Courtnay; Chapman, Frank M; Coues, Elliott, 1842-1899; Forbush, E.H.; Stone, Whitmer; Sutton, George Miksch, b.1898; Thayer, Abbot Handerson, 1849-1921; Van Loon, Hendrik Willem, 1882-1944; Savage Club (Ithaca, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Ornithology--Study and teaching; Birds; Birds in art; Animal painting and illustration.; Natural history illustration.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Photoprints.; Photonegatives.; Sketches.; Sketchbooks; Drawings.; Paintings.
Occupations:
Ornithologists; Artists
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Items labeled as "Ornithology" are on deposit for the Laboratory of Ornithology.
Artwork is arranged in part by old three digit AOU species identification number. Items with 4 digit numbers can be found using the Lab of Ornithology art database. A printed copy of the Fuertes items from this database are with the printed guide.
Access Restrictions:
Access to original artwork is restricted to permission of archivist and requires advance appointment.
Available Copies:
Chronological Field Catalogues #1 and #2 are available on microfilm (positive and negative).
Thesis "The Coloration of Birds" is available on microfilm (positive and negative).
Original of thesis in Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
All artwork and selected photographs have been digitized and are available in the Louis Agassiz Fuertes Ornithological Artwork database.
See also RELATED MATERIALS, below.
RELATED MATERIAL
The Louis Agassiz Fuertes Ornithological Artwork database is a searchable database of 2500 ornithological illustrations by Fuertes. These illustrations have been drawn from Cornell's H.F. Johnson Museum, its Laboratory of Ornithology, the Palmer Collection (Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library), as well as from the Fuertes papers themselves.
The Harriman Alaska Expedition Journal provides both a transcription and digitized copy of a personal journal kept by Fuertes during an 1899 scientific expedition along the Alaskan coast.
See also the Library of Congress exhibit The Harriman Alaska Expedition: Chronicles and Souvenirs May to August 1899, a private souvenir album created collectively by the members of the Alaskan expedition.
See also Joseph Kirkpatrick Bole and William Carnegie Bole collection, #37-5-4304 for photographs of Fuertes and his wife and an original Fuertes pencil drawing.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Boxes 1-19, 33-34
General
Abbot Thayer letters
Savage Club of Ithaca
Mary Fuertes Boynton
Series II. Personal Papers, Loose Sketches, and Manuscript Materials
Boxes 20-23, 29-31, 35, 114, 116, 131 and Map Case Folders 1,3-4
Student Notebooks and Early Sketches
Journals and Field Notebooks
Student Papers and Manuscripts
Various Personal Papers and Loose Sketches
Series III. Printed material (bound)
Box 24
Series IV. Prints and Proofs of Illustrations for Published Works
Box 31, 120, 124
Various Publication
Birds of Massachusetts and Other New England States
Louis Agassiz Fuertes and the Singular Beauty of Birds
Birds of New York by Howard Eaton
Series V. Photographic Materials
Boxes 25-28, 31, 36-38, 46-61, 112, 113, 115, 117, 129, 130
Photographs and 35mm slides
Negatives
Series VII. Artwork
Boxes 41-45, 62-111, 118-128, Map case Folders 6-23, 25 and Framed Items
Arranged by Rare and Manuscript Numbers
Arranged by Laboratory of Ornithology Numbers
Artwork Not Found in Database
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - General
    - October 6, 1892-November 23, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - December 4, 1896-May 13, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - May 15-December 3, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - February 14-December 27, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - January 10-May 16, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - May-July 18, 1899 (Harriman Alaska Expedition) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - August 12-December 29, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - January 2-July 31, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - September 2-December 27, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - January 3-April 6, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - April 13-late May, 1901 (Texas expedition #'s 1-10) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - June 9-July 14, 1901 (Texas expedition #'s 11-16) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - July 19-August 13, 1901 (Texas expedition #'s 17-21) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - August 14-November 26, 1901 (Texas expedition Vs 22-23) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - December 5-29, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - January 5-February 14, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - February 17-April 30, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Late April-June 1902 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - July 9-September 30, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - October 2-November 28, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - December 4-31, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - January 1-February 17, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - February 17-March 1903 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - March 24-April 17, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - April 17-August 12, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - August 14-October 28, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - November 4-December 30, 1903 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - January 4-April 29, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - May 3-December 27, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - January 8-May 12, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - May 16-September 16, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - September 20-December 16, 1905 and n.d. 1905 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - January 11-December 5, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - January 16-August 30, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - September 4-December 28, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Includes November 12 letter from Willard Straight
    - January 2-May 27, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - June 5-October 28, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - October 31, 1908-January 18, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - c. January 1909-March 31, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - April 13, 1909-May 26, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - June 1-July 29, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - August 10 or 11-October 22, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - November 3-December 31, 1909 and n.d. (c. 1909) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - January 3-31, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - February 2-March 31, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - April 3-May 12, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - May 13-June 26, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - June 27-July 18, 1910 (incl. review of "Concealing Coloration in the Animal Kingdom" by Chapman) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - July 21-August 31, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - September 2-November 30, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - December 4-26, 1910 and c. 1910 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - January 5-February 28, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - March 1-April 24, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - May 2-July 29, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - August 2-30, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - c. September 1-October 25, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - November 7-December 15, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - December18-31, 1911 and c. 1911 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - January 1-31, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - February 2-28, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - March 1-27, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - April2-30, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - May 1-28, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - June1-30, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - July 1-30, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - August 8-October 8, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - October 9-November 25, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - November 26-December 17, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - December 18-31, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - January 2-April 24, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - May 2-June 17, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - June 18-July 31, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - August3 or 4-September 29, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - October 1-25, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - October 28-December 10, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - December 10-December 31, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - January 1-March 2, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - March 3-April 23, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - April 25-May 28, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - June 1-August 31, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - September 9-November 5, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - November 10-December 9, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - December 11-31, 1914 and n.d. (c. 1914) (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - January 1-31, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - February 1-21 1915 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - March1-31, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - April1-21, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - April 22-May 6, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - May 11-June 31 and c. June 1915 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - July 2-August 31, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - September 1-27, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - September 28-October 13, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - October 14-November 8, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - November 9-29, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - December 1-21, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - December 21-31, 1915 and n.d. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - January 3-31, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - February 1-25, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - February 25-March 14, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - March 14-31, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - April4-30, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - May 2-23, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - May 24-June 21, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - June 22-30, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - July 1-31, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - August 2-29, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - September 2-October 5, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - October 5-31, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - November 4-30, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - December 1-13, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - December14-26, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - December27-31, 1916 and c. 1916 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - January 1-15, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - January 16-24, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - January 25-February 7, 1917 and c. January 1917 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - February 8-22, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - February 23-March 9, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - March 10-31, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - April1-30, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - May 2-29, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - June 20-July 28, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - August 30-September 28, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - October 1-30, 1917 and c. 1917 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - November2-28, 1917 and c. November 1917 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - December2-30, 1917 and c. 1917 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - January 1-31, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - February 5-28, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - March 1-28, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - April 1-29, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - May 2-June 26 and n.d. May 1918 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - June 27-July 27, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - August 3-September 30, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - October1-26, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - October 28-December 5, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - December 7-31, 1918 and c. 1918 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - January 2-31, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - February1-28, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - March 1-31, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - April 9-31, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - May 1-31, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - June 2-30, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - July 1-August 26, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - September 2-October 20, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - October 21-November 29, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - December 1-20, 1919 and c. 1919 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - January 3-30, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - February 2-28, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - March 1-23, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - March 24-April 9, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - April 9-22, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - May 1-29, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - June 1-30, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - July 1-30, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - August 8-September 20, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - October 1-November 30, 1920 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - December 3-30, 1920 and n.d. 1920 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - January 4-31, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - February 2-18, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - February 19-March 10, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - March 10-31, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - April 1-30, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - May 3-25, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - May 26-June 11, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - June 20-August 11, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - August 12-September 30, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - October 3-November 15, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - November 16-December 21, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - December 22-31, and n.d. 1921 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - January 5-February 27, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - March 1-31, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - April1-30, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - May 1-June 30, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - July 1-August 22, 1922 (Letter of August 22 includes a copy of "Conservation and the Public Mind.") (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - September 4-October 31, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - November 2-December 30, 1922 and n.d. 1922 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - January 2-30, 1923 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - February 1-March 30, 1923 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - April 5-30, 1923 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - May 2-June 19, 1923 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - July 3-September 10, 1923 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - September10-28, 1923 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - October 1-31, 1923 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - November 1-24, 1923 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - November 25-December 29, 1923 and n.d. 1923 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - January 2-February 23, 1924 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - March 6-April 29, 1924 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - May 3-June 29, 1924 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - July 3-31, 1924 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - August 4-31, 1924 and c. July and August 1924 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - September 6-October 31, 1924 and n.d. (c. October 1924) (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - November 1-December 11, 1924 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - December 12-31 and c. 1924 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - January 1-31, 1925 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - February 2-27, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - March 2-April 30, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - May 4-June 14, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - June 15-July 24, 1925 and c. July 1925 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - August 1-September 27, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - October 1-November 29, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - December 1-31, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - January 4-February 28, 1926 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - March 3-April 17, 1926 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - April 19-30, 1926 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - May 3-June 20, 1926 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - June 21-August 2, 1926 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - August 2-30, 1926 and c. July and August 1926 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - September 1-22, 1926 and c. September 1926 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - October 3-29, 1926 and c. October-December 1926 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - November 12, 1926-May 10, 1927 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - May 12-June 3, 1927 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - June 9-December 24, 1927 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - n.d. A-C (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - n.d. D-F (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - G-K (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - L-O (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - P-S (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - T,W (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence with Frederick H. Kennard,1912-1924 and n.d. (ADDITIONAL) (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence with Hendrik Willem van Loon, 1933 and 1943 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Abbot Thayer letters
    - Thayer, 1896-1897 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Thayer, 1898-1900 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Thayer, 1901-1903 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Thayer, 1909-1912 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Thayer, 1913-1917 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Savage Club of Ithaca correspondence, January-June 1915
    - January 21-May 19, 1915 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - May 20-June 4. 1915 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Mary Fuertes Boynton. Contains correspondence between Dr. Boynton and acquaintances, friends and collegues of her father concerning his work, life and papers.
    - July-October 1941 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - November 1941-March 1942 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - April 1942-December 1943, n.d. 1943 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - March 1947-October 1949 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - November-December 1949 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - January-May 1950 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - June-December 1950 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - January 1951-May 1952 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - January 1953-March 1954 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - September 1963 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Index to correspondence
    - Alphabetical card file recording correspondents, dates, box/folder numbers (Box 33-34)
- Series II. Personal Papers, Loose Sketches, and Manuscript Materials
  - Student Notebooks and Early Sketches
    - Herbarium and Plant Description includes pressed specimens (fragile), 1892 (Box 20)
    - Mineralogy - includes architectural sketches, lecture notes, c. 1895 (Box 20)
    - German Literature lecture notes and other notes, 1895 (Box 20)
    - Proofs Corrected and Accepted for the Seventh Report of the New York Forest, Fish and Game Commission lithographs with annotations, 1901 (Box 20)
    - Notes on Geology and Lithology, 1895 (Box 20)
    - Plant Physiology, Botany, Course 1 Lecture, 1895 (Box 20)
    - Physics Notes, c. 1895 (Box 20)
    - Anatomical Methods - Notes, 1895 (Box 20)
    - Details and Sketches of Railings, Mouldings, etc., 1895 (Box 20)
    - Notes on Physics Lectures, 1894 (Box 20)
    - 'History of England - Geography Notes, c. 1895 Notes on Physics - Sound and Optics (Box 20)
    - Birds, c. 1889 (Box 131)
    - Botany, c. 1892 (Box 131)
    - Report - Histology, 1897 (Box 131)
    - Report on the Work in Histology, 1896 (Box 131)
    - Report - Histological Laboratory, 1897 (Box 131)
    - Comparison Between the Scapulae of Man and the Cat (Box 131)
    - The Humerus of Man, 1895 (Box 131)
    - Entomology Practicum, 1896 (Box 131)
    - Report on First Week's Work - Histology, 1897 (Box 131)
    - Report on Third Week's Work - Histology Digestive and Respiratory Systems, 1897 (Box 131)
    - Materials of Constructions, 1894 (Box 131)
    - Statistical Catalogue of Birds (Box 131)